Let's continue now. So, דף כ"ו עמוד ב'. Daf Chaf Vav Amud
Bet. אמר
רב הונא אמר רב. Amar Rav Huna Amar Rav.
We're still, don't worry, we only have one, hopefully if we get
fast enough, far enough today, we will finish this topic today. But
the rest of this until the next משנה Mishnah is this issue
about this unspecified pile of money. אמר רב הונא אמר רב, Amar
Rav Huna Amar Rav, לא שנו אלא מעות. Lo Shanu Ela Maot.
This idea that if you have unspecified pile of money that was
going to be used for חטאת, Chatas, עולה, Olah, and שלמים Shlamim
of a נזיר Nazir and the guy dies or the נזירות Nezirus
was annulled by the husband, that then it goes towards an עולה,
Olah, that's only if it was a pile of money. אבל בהמה
הרי היא כמפורשת. Aval Behemah Harei Hi K'mifureshet. If it was animals,
it's like it's explicit. Now, what's the case of animals? Let me
explain. What's the case of animals? So a lot of these long
תוספות Tosafos here are just to get basic פשט Pshat in the
גמרא Gemara because it's a very terse גמרא. Gemara. תוספות Tosafos goes
through all the possibilities. Maybe the animals were the animals that a
נזיר Nazir is supposed to bring: a lamb, a male lamb, a
female lamb, a ram, and so on. But if that were true,
then it would be so obvious then you had sanctified all the
animals, and each animal,
the עולה, Olah, חטאת, Chatas, and שלמים Shlamim are all different animals.
So it would be self-obvious, of course it's מפורשים, Mefurashim, this is
for that sacrifice, this is for that, each one is a different
animal. So what תוספות Tosafos says is it sounds like what the
גמרא Gemara is talking about is that actually no, what you have
is three cows here.
You have animals that maybe are in the world of
sacrifices, wouldn't work if they were let's say three pigs, you got
three cows, but none of them are relevant for this sacrifice. And
somehow you say: I am sanctifying all of these animals for the
purpose of bringing my sacrifices. And basically what that's going to mean
is you're going to have to redeem the value, transfer the value,
or sell it, get the proceeds, and use the money to buy
your sacrifices. Now the other interesting הלכה Halacha that תוספות Tosafos works
out, which I'll just tell you because the גמרא Gemara is going
to distinguish between whether the animals have a מום Mum or don't
have a מום, Mum, is the following interesting question. If I go
ahead and I say: I am sanctifying this lovely here digital recorder
to use to bring my עולה. Olah.
I'm going to bring an עולה Olah from the funds of this.
Fine, so what I do is I go ahead, I sell it
or the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash sells it or whatever, I redeem
the money, I get the proceeds, the value transfers to the proceeds
I get from the sale, and then I use that money to
go ahead and buy the animal that I need to buy. That
would be normally okay. It's not קדושת בדק הבית, Kedushas Bedek HaBayis,
it's not like I donated this to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
and it can sell it and use it for its upkeep or
for its operating funds. This I could, but that's not what I
did. I actually gave this recorder the קדושה Kedusha of an עולה.
Olah. Great, but you don't bring recorders as עולות. Olot. So that
קדושה Kedusha transfers to the money like when I set aside the
money for my קרבנות. Korbanot. It has the קדושה Kedusha of the
קרבן, Korban, but it's not going to be used itself, you're going
to then transfer it eventually to the animal. That's what would normally
happen. Let's say I go ahead and I sanctify my goat, my
cow,
for my קרבן נזיר Korban Nazir which has to be a sheep.
So can I just go ahead and sell the cow and use
the proceeds?
Why not? Because if let's say I had actually here three scenarios.
One is I sanctify the cow for the בדק הבית, Bedek HaBayis,
for the operating funds, upkeep of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. They
just sell it, right? It's just a cow. Fine, it's just like
I sanctified my car. Here's scenario number two: I sanctify the cow
to bring the cow itself as an עולה. Olah. In that case,
if I would want to not bring that cow, I couldn't just
transfer the money, I'd have to wait for the cow to get
a מום. Mum. Here is an interesting middle so if it's just
being used as something as an object of value, not in its
identity as a cow, basically just as an object of value like
a car, you sell it right away. If it's being used because
it itself was going to be brought as a קרבן, Korban, the
transfer can only be the קדושה Kedusha can only be transferred if
it has a מום. Mum. Let's say I gave it the קדושה
Kedusha of a קרבן Korban but not for it itself to be
brought as a קרבן. Korban. I gave it the קדושה Kedusha of
an עולה Olah but the עולה Olah of a נזיר Nazir can
only be brought from a sheep. So because it has the קדושה
Kedusha that's relevant to the world of קרבנות, Korbanot, and if it
itself was a קרבן, Korban, that קדושה Kedusha cannot be removed without
a מום. Mum. Now that I gave it this קדושה, Kedusha, does
that mean that the קדושה Kedusha can't be removed without a מום?
Mum? Or do we say look, since you're not going to bring
this cow itself, you can just automatically sell it and transfer the
קדושה, Kedusha, you don't need a מום? Mum? So that's what תוספות
Tosafos tries to sort of figure out and work out, and based
on this סוגיא Sugya that's what we're going to see in a
minute, you haven't even seen the גמרא Gemara yet, תוספות Tosafos concludes
that yes, because it's relevant to the world of קרבנות, Korbanot, because
in theory it could be brought itself even though that's not the
קדושה Kedusha you gave it right now, you cannot get the קדושה
Kedusha off of that cow, even though it's coming for a sheep
עולה, Olah, until the cow has a מום. Mum. So if you
had sanctified, I don't know, a chicken,
with the קדושה Kedusha of an עולה, Olah, you could sell it,
you just sell it to the farmer, you get the money. But
because it's a cow and the cow is relevant to the world
of קרבנות. Korbanot. Okay, even though you did not give it the
קדושה kedushah for it itself to be brought, the קדושה kedushah cannot
be removed without it somehow being out, removed from the world of
קרבנות. korbanot. That's the only way it can sort of free itself
from that קדושה. kedushah. Otherwise it's just too relevant to that קדושה
kedushah that it cannot be transferred just through an act of sale.
Okay, so that's what תוספות Tosafot says. The reason that's going to
be relevant before I take the questions, let's just read the line
in the גמרא Gemara which makes this all very relevant. So the
next line in the גמרא Gemara says the following, and then I'll
explain anyway what this has to do with whether how the funds
are used or or not. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
אמר רב נחמן הדא דאמרי בהמה הרי היא כמפורשת. Amar Rav Nachman,
hada d'amri behemah harei hi k'mefureshet. That statement of רב Rav that
a בהמה behemah is like it's already been designated, לא שנו אלא
תמימה, lo shanu ela temimah, that's only if it's an unblemished בהמה.
behemah. And in that type of a case, again, even if we're
dealing with cows here, but the money cannot be the, they cannot
just be simply sold. You have to wait for them to get
a blemish, and that's what gives them a different status. אבל בעלת
מום, Aval ba'alat mum, if these cows had a blemish, okay, הרי
כסתומה, harei k'stumah, then it's like unspecified funds. Now, okay, so now
I've laid the groundwork for us to understand the difference that even
if we're dealing with cows and animals that cannot themselves be brought
for this sacrifice, why it matters if there's a blemish or not
a blemish or why there's a difference between blemish or not a
blemish, whether they can be sold immediately or not or whether you
have to wait for them to get a blemish. But what still
doesn't explain is why does that make a difference for our הלכה
halacha here about whether it's considered like סתומה stumah or not סתומה,
stumah, whether it's considered like unspecified moneys. If I sanctified three cows
and eventually, whether they do or don't have a blemish, eventually I'm
going to sell them and use the proceeds and divide that proceeds
between the קרבנות korbanot that I have to bring, why should it
be considered like it's סתומה? stumah? Right? Like it's מפורשת! mefureshet! Like
it's already like it's been designated. What do you mean it's been
designated? I mean, it's not like this cow is going to ultimately,
money is going to go to that one, and this cow money
is going to get to that one. I'm going to sell all
three cows and I'm going to divide up the money, right? And
even if I was going to do one cow per sacrifice, which
cow is for which? Why is it like it's מפורשת? mefureshet? It's
all unspecified. Why can't, why wouldn't it have the same הלכה? halacha?
Okay, so that's the question. And that's what we're going to be
dealing with now is things that somehow don't have the status of
unspecified and it's not clear why not. So there basically are two
answers why not. One is the simple הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L'Moshe
MiSinai answer. You know, according to the idea that all of this
is a הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai, the הלכה halacha was
said by money. It wasn't said by things that weren't money. So
if I'm sanctifying something that's not money, even though it really is
סתומה, stumah, it's unspecified, but this הלכה halacha that you get to
reuse that money for an עולה olah if it has the חטאת
chatat money mixed up in it or whatever, that was a special
הלכה halacha only said by cash. It wasn't said by things that
aren't cash. Not cash, okay, it's not מפורשת, mefureshet, that's a funny
way of saying it. It is סתומה, stumah, but it doesn't matter.
The הלכה halacha wasn't said by this and what you'll have to
do is throw it all out into the ים המלח Yam HaMelach
because it has חטאת chatat money mixed with הלכה halacha only said
by cash. Fine. But if it's הלכה halacha only said by cash,
who cares if it's animals that have a blemish? Animals that have
a blemish last I checked also weren't cash. So the question is
what is the line between cash and not cash? And basically, it's
actually, there's an interesting word. It took me a while to realize
this in when I was in when I was in Israel, right?
What's the word for cash in Israel? מזומן. Mezuman. Everyone's like, before
I knew that, I was like, what the heck is מזומן? mezuman?
Ready? What do you mean מזומן? mezuman? I don't understand why that
means cash. Okay, but what it basically means is something that is
very easily immediately transferable, like for the goods that you want, right?
So the basic thinking is like this: something that is like readily
sellable is in the same category and can easily be liquidated and
turned into cash is basically in the same category as cash. So
if you've got animals that have a blemish and all you've got
to do is turn around and sell it to someone, right? Again,
assuming there's a reasonable market for them or whatever, that has a
status of cash. So the הלכה halacha was said by something like
animals with a blemish. It wasn't maybe wouldn't have been said by
I don't know, something like my house. Got put up for sale,
you got to wait for the best bid. That's something, yeah, I
mean I could sell for cash if I really took a serious
loss, but it's not
easily liquidated and easily turned into cash. That's not cash. An animal
without a blemish that has to wait for the blemish before it
could be sold because of the laws of קדושה, kedushah, that is
not in the cash category. That does not, is not easily transferable
into cash. So that is two ways of understanding what we're about
to look at. We're going to say certain things don't have this
הלכה halacha
that you can go ahead and what do you call it, that
you can use the money towards an עולה, olah, this unspecified pile.
Okay, it's only a הלכה halacha said by cash, not things that
aren't cash, and anything that can easily be liquidated and turned into
cash is considered cash. But animals that need a blemish before they're
sold, they're not in that category. Now that doesn't give the logic
for it, it just says in a formal way it's limited to
cash. Okay, the other thing to say and then I know there
are a few questions, but the other thing to say is if
you want a type of a logic for it and this is
where... Spent a lot of time figuring out, does this logic make
sense? He says, here's the logic. The logic is, if it's going
to take me a long time before I can offload this stuff,
so the stuff is going to be around my house a long
time. At a certain stage when I have these three cows grazing
and I'm waiting, waiting, waiting for them to get a blemish, maybe
I'm thinking in my mind, oh, I'm going to sell Bessie over
there, she's going to be for the עולה olah and I'm going
to sell this other one and that one's going to be for
the חטאת, chatat, and in my mind I've somehow already like predesignated,
you know, how I'm going to use that money. And if that
comes about, then it stops having this status of סתומה, stumah, then
it becomes מפורשת mefureshet because I've already decided the funds from that
animal is going to this one and the funds from that animal's
going to that. Now that sounds funny, that sounds like a very
like a rabbinic type of a concern and what תוספות Tosafot deals
with is, and even if I thought that, if I didn't say
that, does it really change the status? I mean, you know, I
haven't said it yet, who cares if I'm thinking that in my
mind. So that's the way he tries to give some logic to
this, but the easier thing is just to make this a formal
rule, that what the גמרא Gemara is saying is, this says only
by cash, something that's going to take time to liquidate and to,
you know, get the cash, the money for and to ultimately buy
the other thing, that this הלכה halacha was not said for and
that's not considered the idea that you use the money for an
עולה, olah, in that case you would throw it all out, you
have to treat it because there's חטאת chatat money in here, you'd
have to throw it all out. Okay, so now I'm done with
my explanation. Was there a question?
Okay, all right good, yeah.
And the question is this, so you're saying the case was that
he set aside cows or whatever it is? Right. So
that, I guess in my mind, my question is, doesn't that harken
back, I think it was מחלוקת בית הלל ובית שמאי, machlokes Beit
Hillel v'Beit Shammai, הקדש בטעות? hekdesh b'ta'ut?
It's not תוספות, Tosafot, I knew that I wasn't going to bring
the things itself, but as a, as a famous setting aside, but
maybe yes, but the same as setting aside a pile of money,
I set aside three cows. Okay, so that's his point, okay. אבל
נסכא לא, Aval nascha lo, but if it was נסכא nascha
which was basically like a bar of precious metal, a bar of
silver or a bar of gold or something like that,
that would not, meaning would not be a problem that basically something
like that, hold on, I keep on getting confused which way this
one goes. No, that would, that also would not be considered like
cash, that would be something that you would actually,
you'd have to, you don't just sell quickly, you'd have to wait
till you got the right price for it and so on, so
that's sort of like the animals without the blemish, that's also not
cash.
Why is that not like a recorder?
Well, again, there's a difference between a recorder, you know, now we
put these things on eBay or Craigslist and we could probably sell
them pretty quickly, but there's not like as much of a ready
market for recorders as there are for cows. You live in an
agricultural society you just go to the market next week and somebody's
going to, you know, sell your cows, right?
So cows are more readily available than a bar of gold?
That seems to be the assumption and, or right, or maybe it's
harder to ensure you're getting your right price, although you would think
precious metal it goes by weight maybe it's easier, I don't know,
but that's the assumption here that these types of things are things
you have to wait more to get the right price for that
don't sell as
easily. Okay. רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר אפילו נסכא, Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak amar afilu nascha,
no, no, no, even bar of metal is considered something that is
cash for this purpose and therefore it has this הלכה halacha that
the money goes towards an עולה, olah, אבל סובי דקארי, aval sovi
d'karei, but if you've got a pile of like beams of, you
know, of lumber, in that case, you know, beams of wood, לא,
lo, not, because again, I don't know, like, you know, that's something
that you have to find the person that's looking to construct a
house and he's got to inspect it, whatever it is, that's not
as liquid as these other things. So it's an interesting question of
how liquid something has to be in order to be considered cash
in order to have this special הלכה. halacha. Fine. אמר ליה רב
שימי בר אשי לרב פפא, Amar lei Rav Shimi bar Ashi l'Rav
Pappa, רב שימי בר אשי Rav Shimi bar Ashi says to רב
פפא, Rav Pappa, מאי טעמא דרבנן, mai ta'ama d'rabbanan,
what's the reason of the רבנן rabbanan that say, you know, that
it only applies to money? דאמרי דמים ולא בהמה ולא נסכא, D'amri
damim v'lo behema v'lo nascha, because they say this הלכה halacha was
said by money, מעות, mo'ot, means not animals, again with a, that
you have to wait for a blemish at least, okay, and not
bars
of precious metal, דמים ולא סוורא, damim v'lo savra,
not a, or סובי, sovi, not a, you know, a pile of
lumber, not lumber, a pile of like beams. As that's what they
say, it has to be only money and these things aren't considered
cash. אלא מעתה, Ela mei'ata, if that's true, דמים ולא עופות, damim
v'lo ofot,
let's say money and not birds. Now, what does he mean by
birds? You think okay, I'm sanctifying these birds to be used for
my קרבן נזיר. korban nazir. All right, well, you know, maybe we
would say that, again, would depend on how readily transferable birds would
be, you know, to cash and so on. But what's going to
be clear from the גמרא Gemara and that's what takes up this
huge תוספות, Tosafot, which means that our דף daf is going to
go quickly. is that it doesn't read in the ongoing discussion. We're
not just talking like you sanctified some chickens or something like that,
okay? But what we're talking about is that this other הלכה halakha
which I think actually
was mentioned the other day, which was if a woman, well the
classic case is a woman, but anybody who has to bring two
birds, an עולה ola and a חטאת, chatas, classic case is a
woman who's given birth, and she sanctifies the birds, she doesn't have
to specify which is the עולה, ola, which is the חטאת. chatas.
She can either do it at the time she sanctifies them, or
the כהן kohen is the one that specifies when the כהן kohen
brings them. That's the הלכה. halakha. Okay, so what we're going to
say is that the question here is now I've got to remind
myself because תוספות Tosafos has three possibilities and I'll tell you what
the third one is at the very end of
this
תוספות. Tosafos.
Hold on.
Okay,
so here's the question תוספות Tosafos asks. What would be the case
in the following case? We've been focusing so far on the money
of a נזיר nazir or whatever that has to be for three
קרבנות. korbanos. The נזיר nazir dies. What do you use the money
for? Let's say we had another case. A woman went ahead, she
was obligated in a קרבן korban for a יולדת. yoledes. Two birds.
She brought the two birds. One was going to be a חטאת,
chatas, one was going to be an עולה. ola. She didn't specify
which was which. Okay? She would have brought it to the כהן,
kohen, the כהן kohen would have specified. Then the woman died before
she was able to bring it. What do you do with those
two birds? So what would you think you do with those two
birds? One
of them is a חטאת, chatas, one is an עולה. ola. So
maybe you bring it to the כהן kohen and let the כהן
kohen decide which one is an עולה ola and bring that and
maybe the other one get rid of, right?
Because she died, right? She died. But you said the other day
that if somebody died the חטאת chatas offering can't be brought.
It can't be brought, the חטאת. chatas.
You can bring the עולה. ola.
Right. So you would assume that since if she was alive she
would bring it to the כהן, kohen, the כהן kohen would pick
out, would decide which is the חטאת, chatas, which is an עולה.
ola. She died, let the כהן kohen do the same thing, right?
Okay. But how about this as a possibility? Let's consider those two
birds like the pile of unspecified money that had in it a
חטאת chatas and an עולה, ola, and let's say that both birds
now become an עולה, ola, okay, like the pile of money that
has a חטאת chatas and an עולה ola mixed up in it
and you bring from that pile you bring an עולה, ola, so
let's now make both birds into an עולה. ola. Okay? That's the,
that would be the alternative. Okay? So the question is, if you
were to consider this pile to be like סתומים, stumim, okay, like
unspecified, like a normal case of סתומים, stumim, maybe we should say
that that should be the הלכה. halakha. So that's the question that
the גמרא Gemara is actually going to explore, okay? And so now
what, so let's take a look. Let's read the next line.
Okay, but what's the difference between that and the money that was
unspecified?
Well,
that's the question. Since we're already saying that the idea of unspecified
funds has some of these arbitrary limits, like it's only money and
it's not cows and it's not this and it's not that, what
if it was birds? Okay? If you had these birds, which basically
had קדושה kedusha of חטאת chatas and an עולה ola mixed in
here. Now the difference is obvious, because in the case of birds,
the beings themselves are going to be brought as opposed to using
the proceeds to buy something, okay? So you could say if the
thing itself has that potential קדושה, kedusha, you know, you can't transfer,
you know, the קדושה kedusha doesn't transform in the thing itself that
was going to be brought. But anyway, but we're going to step
back and we're going to say, look, exactly that. You know, maybe
we should say there isn't a difference and maybe we should say
bring them both as an עולה. ola. But maybe, since you've just
demonstrated that you have all these arbitrary rules here, it only is
money and not things like this and not things like that and
not things like that, so maybe also in the bird case, that's
also something that you would be, would not fit into this category.
And because maybe it's a very limited category and maybe you would
not be able to bring both of the birds as an עולה.
olah. So that's the question. Our initial assumption would have been that
these two birds are like מעות סתומים. ma'ot stumin. Are, you have
the potential, you have a חטאת chatat and an עולה olah mixed
up in these two birds. The person died, we should treat it
like מעות סתומים ma'ot stumin and we should get to bring both
of them as an עולה. olah. But given that you've just told
me how narrow your category is and you're excluding all these other
things, maybe we should exclude a case of birds as well and
not allow them to be brought both as an עולה. olah. That's
the question. Okay? So let's see.
They haven't even been designated yet, that's why they're like סתומים. stumim.
Okay, so let's take a look. Okay, אלא מעתה, ella me'ata, that's
true. מעות ולא עופות, ma'ot velo ofot, let's say that it won't
apply to a case of non-specified birds that you won't be able
to bring both of those as an עולה. olah. וכי תימא הכי
נמי, vechi teima hachi nami, maybe that's true. Maybe it's true. If
the woman dies or whatever, you don't get to bring them both
as an עולה. olah. אלא הא דאמר רב חסדא, ella had'amar Rav
Chisda, but רב חסדא Rav Chisda taught, אין
הקינין מתפרשות אלא אם בלקיחת בעלים או בעשיית הכהן. ein hakinim mitparshot
ella im belikichat be'alim o be'asiyat hacohen. The birds do not get
their identity, do not get explicated, right? מתפרשות mitparshot is the opposite
of סתום. satum. סתום satum is מפורש. mufarash. They don't get explicated
and they don't get identified either only at the time that they're
purchased by the owner or when the כהן cohen actually brings it.
Okay. Now, אמאי? amai? But why is that true? המעות קאמינא לך,
hama'ot kamina lach, it should have been only money and not birds.
Now what does רב חסדא Rav Chisda say that tells us that
this idea that if the woman dies, you know, he's talking about
the woman's alive and they get either explained either at the time
of purchase or the time of the כהן cohen brought, how's that
relevant for our discussion? So it's not so clear at all how
it's relevant for our discussion, but תוספות Tosafot says it's because he
chose to use the word מתפרשות. mitparshot. And מתפרשות mitparshot is the
opposite of סתום. satum. Right he could have said another word. He
said אין הקינין נקבעים, ein hakinim nikba'im, their identity isn't established except
when they're purchased by the person or brought by the כהן. cohen.
But he says they're not explicated מתפרשות, mitparshot, it means that without
that stage of being identified at the time of purchase or by
the כהן, cohen, if they're not מתפרשות, mitparshot, what is their halachic
status? So what's the opposite of מפורש? mufarash? סתום. satum. So it's
basically implicitly what he is saying is until if the woman hasn't
said it at the time she purchased it and the כהן cohen
has yet to bring it, their status is סתום. satum. And if
that's their halachic status as סתומים, stumim, where we have a הלכה
halacha for סתומים, stumim, you've got this stuff that's סתום, satum, the
owner dies, what do you do with it? You bring it as
a נדבה. nedava. So the גמרא Gemara wants to infer from the
fact that he used the word מתפרשות, mitparshot, this is the way
תוספות Tosafot reads. Again, there's a lot of other reads that are
even worse than this, so if you're not so satisfied with this
read, it's the best of the three of this huge תוספות. Tosafot.
So the birds
remain סתום satum if the woman dies, that's what we're getting out
of him, which means it follows the normal הלכה halacha of סתומים,
stumim, which means they both go towards an עולה. olah. But he's
saying but now the גמרא's Gemara question is, why do they both
go towards an עולה? olah? You've been so narrow in your definition,
only money, not metal, not wood, not this, not that, so let's
also say not birds. Why is the הלכה halacha that in this
case both of those birds go towards an עולה? olah? Okay, that's
the question. Let's read the answer. אמר ליה, amar lei, he said
back to him, ולטעמיך, uleta'ameicha, and one minute, according to your reasoning,
you want to say that you want to reject my whole idea.
And you want to say that it doesn't matter, money, birds, animals,
bars of metal, all of that the same הלכה halacha applies, and
that if it's סתום, satum, it goes towards an עולה. olah. That's
the opposite opinion. Don't have any of these limitations. If that's true,
הדתנן, hadatnan, that which we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, הביא שלש בהמות, heivi
shalosh behemot, you brought three animals, ולא פירש, velo peresh, and you
didn't say, you brought three animals in front of you, one male
sheep, one female sheep, and one ram, and you basically said I'm
sanctifying these three animals for my sacrifices as a נזיר, nazir, as
a נזיר. nazir. Now just it just so happens that those are
the exact three animals you need. Okay so but you didn't explain
which is which. So guess what? It all works out. You know,
if you're generic and they're the right animals, the קדושה kedusha gets
assigned appropriately. הראויה לחטאת תקרב חטאת לעולה תקרב עולה ולשלמים תקרב שלמים.
harauya lechatat tikarev chatat le'olah tikarev olah velishlamim tikarev shlamim.
Each animal gets assigned for its right identity. Okay fine, that's not
much of a חידוש, chiddush, I mean that would be a pretty
logical thing to say. But one minute, you want to say now
that this הלכה halacha of סתומים stumim applies regardless of the thing
that is non-specified, whether it's money, whether it's pieces of wood, whether
it's pieces of metal, whether it's animals, it all has the הלכה
halacha of סתומים. stumim. That's the counterargument. Not to limit it to
the money idea. So if that's true, אמאי, amai, why should this
קדושה kedusha get divided like just so conveniently? אמרת בהמה לאו כמפורשת
דמי, amarta behema lav kemufareshet dami,
an animal is still is not like explicated, it's like in the
category of סתום. satum. So if it's like in the category of
סתום, satum, even in this case we should say they're all סתומים
stumim and... they don't have any specific identity, which shows us this
is crazy. It's one thing if I take three cows and cows
aren't relevant to the sacrifice and I say if I sanctify those
three cows for the proceeds to go, that has this הלכה halacha
of non-specified סתום, satum, it hasn't yet been identified which is which
and then if the guy dies, the money will go, you know,
whatever, that's fine. But if you got the right animals and you're
sanctifying them, of course it's not סתום, satum, of course it's going
to be defined in the proper way. Okay, so it's such a
difficult גמרא, Gemara, I don't have a good answer to that question.
I mean, what type of question are you raising from this? Here
it's the right animals, of course they're going to be have the
right קדושה, kedusha, they're not going to be, he doesn't have a
good one, they're not going to be non-specified.
Anyway, let's read a little bit more in the גמרא. Gemara. אמר
ליה, Amar leh, he said back to him, he basically התם ולקח
ועשה אמר רחמנא. hasam velakach ve'asah amar Rachmana. By the case of
birds, the Torah says, you take and you do. אי בלקיחת בעלים
אי בעשיית כהן. ee belakichat ba'alim ee be'asiyat Kohen.
Its identity is defined either at the time that the owner does
it or at the כהן. Kohen. These birds, which it's not yet,
which didn't have the בעלים ba'alim yet and haven't had the כהן
Kohen yet and the person died, so their קדושה kedusha is not
specified. That's what the Torah tells you. It's not specified קדושה. kedusha.
And by the way, it's the exact same bird is a חטאת
chatat or an עולה. olah. So of course it's not going to
be able to be identified which is which. So the birds can
have a status of non-specified. That's possible. הכא נמי hacha nami here,
מי מצית
אמרת? mi matzet amart? How,
here how could you say that it's not specified? הדין דחטאת תיקריב
עולה? hadin dechatat tikeriv olah? How could you say that the one
that's a חטאת chatat should be brought as an עולה? olah? How
could you, you can't say non-specified here, they're different animals, okay? הכא
נקבה הכא זכר. hacha nekeva hacha zachar. The חטאת chatat is a
female, the עולה's olah a male. So that's a silly question which
is so obvious, of course it's a silly question. We can talk
about non-specified when any one could be used for it, right? When
it really could easily be any. So it was a completely bizarre
question. Oh, well, by the animals of course you see that of
course, you know, that it is animals are defined as specified. Yeah,
self-identified, clear,
clearly distinguished animals that fall into appropriate categories are specified. But non-distinguished
animals, right, that all sort of generic, of course, why shouldn't they
be? Okay, so we, so that was a bizarre question. But the
basic point is, you have the initial position which is, the הלכה
halacha was basically said by money. And you have this counter-position that
says we shouldn't be limiting it to money. Whether it's money, whether
it's animals, whether it's bars of metal, if it's not specified, it's
not specified. Don't ask me from a question when you happen to
have the exact right animals. Of course if you have the right
animals, that's like, it's like you have three piles of money and
one had a big עולה olah sign and a חטאת chatat sign
and a שלמים shelamim sign, he said I'm sanctifying this money, okay,
that's also not specified because it's clear. If you have the right
animals, of course it's clear. But if you don't have the right
animals, okay, the other position says it doesn't matter whether it's money
or anything else. It all follows the same הלכות. halachas. So that's
the question. Is the הלכה halacha basically said only by money, or
is it basically said by everything? And interestingly, one of the applications
is this idea of birds. If the הלכה halacha is said not
limited to money, then this case which is the woman who buys
the two birds and gets defined when she takes it or when
the כהן Kohen brings it, and she were to die, well then
that would also be seen as non-specified
קדושה kedusha and the הלכה halacha would be that we would bring
both of them as an עולה. olah. Okay, so let's read a
little bit more. I think there were some questions but I want
to get a little bit further here, get us a little out
of the woods here. So, מתיב רב המנונא. mative Rav Hamnuna. Rav
Hamnuna asked. מי אמרינן בהמה
בעלת מום כסתומה דמיא? mi
amrinan behema ba'alat mum kestuma
damya?
Is
it really true that an animal with a מום mum is like
סתומה stuma because that was the one we said that actually would
be like cash, right? If it had a מום, mum, even according
to the approach that limits it to cash and to money, an
animal with a מום mum is seen as readily, you know, liquidatable,
liqui-what's the word? Liquidatable? Liquefiable? Anyway, not fungible, anyway, anyway, easily liquidated,
easily turned into cash, and that would have a status of cash.
What? לגבי מום? legabei mum? Who cares, it's a מום, mum, I
want it to plow my field, I go to the farmers market
on, you know, okay, wait a minute, if you, so according to
this approach that you need cash, but a בהמה behema with a
מום mum
that doesn't have a קדושה kedusha problem and therefore can be sold
right away is considered like cash. תא שמע, ta shema, let me
count you this. כיצד אמרו איש מגלח על נזירות אביו? keitsad amru
ish megalbeach al nezirut aviv? When did we say that a father,
a person can shave for his father's נזירות? nezirut?
To shave here also basically means brings the קרבנות korbanot for his
father's נזירות. nezirut.
Now this ברייתא braita here, this is actually quoted in a chopped
up way here and it's not clear, so if you take a
quick look to ל' עמוד ב', lamed amud bet, which is where
the ברייתא braita originally appears, I don't know, originally, whatever, it's just
quoted in full there. So just turn for a minute to ל'
עמוד ב' lamed amud bet and look three lines from the top
on ל' עמוד ב'. lamed amud bet. Okay, it says the following:
כיצד אמרו איש מגלח על נזירות אביו? keitsad amru ish megalbeach al
nezirut aviv? מי שהיה אביו נזיר, mishehaya aviv nazir, the father was
a נזיר, nazir, והפריש. vehefrish. והפריש אביו מעות לנזירותו. Vehifrish aviv maot
leneziruto.
So again, father set aside money, ומת, Umet, and the father died.
Now, if there wasn't a child here, then the money we would
say would go towards an עולה. Olah. That's what we've been saying.
But now here's an interesting special case about what we've been talking
about. ואמר, Ve'amar, the son says, הריני נזיר על מנת שאגלח על
מעות אבא. Hareini nazir al menat she'agalei'ach al maot Abba. אבא, Abba,
you know what? אבא, Abba, I'll be a נזיר Nazir as long
as I get to use my father's money for my קרבנות. Korbanot.
That's what אגלח Agalei'ach means. Okay, so you have this pile of
money which would have gone towards an עולה Olah because the נזיר
Nazir died. And then now the son says, you know what? I'll
use that money for mine as long as it was as long
as
number one, it was an unspecified pile. And number two is he
accepted the נזירות Nezirut after his father died. So the money was
no longer able to be used for its original purpose. It was
standing there with say undefined purpose as of yet. Okay, so the
father had died and then he accepted his נזירות Nezirut specifically with
the right, you know, assuming he was entitled to use that money,
then he actually does get to use that money for his קרבנות.
Korbanot. זהו שמגלח על מעות אביו. Zehu shemegalei'ach al maot aviv. That
person gets to bring the קרבנות Korbanot with his father's money. אבל
מי שהיה הוא ואביו נזירים. Aval mi shehayah hu ve'aviv nezirim. He
and his father were נזירים Nezirim at the same time. Okay, he
didn't wait for his father to die. והפריש אביו מעות לנזירותו ומת,
Vehifrish aviv maot leneziruto umet, and then the father died and the
money had been sanctified for the father's thing. הרי אלו יפלו לנדבה.
Harei elu yiplu linedavah. Then he you don't get to use that
money for his נזירות, Nezirut, that has the normal הלכה Halachah that
it goes towards the עולה. Olah. Okay, so that's the הלכה. Halachah.
Let's jump back to our גמרא Gemara and see how it's being
used. Okay, so turning back to our גמרא, Gemara, כז עמוד ב,
Chaf Zayin Amud Bet, תא שמע. Ta shema. כיצד אמרו האיש מגלח
על נזירות אביו. Keitzad amru ha'ish megalei'ach al nezirut aviv.
Okay,
so it cut out the line that when it does work that's
when the father died and then he said I'll be a
נזיר. Nazir. However, היה הוא ואביו נזירים, Hayah hu ve'aviv nezirim, it
sort of skips jumps to the second case. This case it doesn't
work is he and his father were נזירים. Nezirim. והפריש אביו מעות
לנזירותו ומת, Vehifrish aviv maot leneziruto umet, and the father set aside
money and then the father died. ואמר הריני נזיר על מנת שאגלח
על מעות אבא, Ve'amar hareini nazir al menat she'agalei'ach al maot Abba,
and he said I'm going to use my father's money. So he
can't do that now because he was already a נזיר Nazir before
his father, you know, before his father died. So הרי אלו יפלו
לנדבה. Harei elu yiplu linedavah.
Okay,
in that case he's not entitled to use the father's money and
you do with the money what you normally would do, which would
be unspecified money goes towards a נדבה. Nedavah. היתה לו בהמה מפורשת,
Haitah lo behemah meforeshet, if however
the animal had been already identified. חטאת תמות, Chatat tamut, the animal
that's a חטאת Chatat you let die. עולה תקרב עולה, Olah takarev
olah, עולה Olah you bring עולה. Olah. שלמים יפלו לשלמים. Shlamim yiplu
lishlamim.
Okay,
so so far doesn't say anything especially in that case much new.
Unspecified money goes towards an עולה, Olah, specified animals go towards their
right thing. So how are we using this? מאי לאו, Mai lav,
says the גמרא, Gemara, אפילו בעלת מום. Afilu ba'alat mum. Look,
when it says if you've got the animal you can't get to
use you don't get to use the money for an עולה, Olah,
presumably by once you have animals that sort of they're and they're
used for their right purpose, presumably that would even include cases of
non-specified animals with blemishes, which is like crazy because that's not the
case in the משנה, Mishnah, the ברייתא. Braita. The case is that
it's very clear. This is the חטאת, Chatat, this is the עולה.
Olah. It is clearly explicit. But the גמרא Gemara somehow thinks since
you're
contrasting money to animals, any case of animals would be different. Any
case of animals would not be like money because it's trying to
support this idea with this idea of are animals like money or
not. So presumably all cases of animals, even non-specified animals, even animals
with blemishes would not be like money. Isn't that what it's saying?
So מאי לאו אפילו בעלת מום? Mai lav afilu ba'alat mum? לא
תמימה. Lo temimah. No, we're talking about that the animals are unblemished
or even more that the animals are clearly specified. אבל בעלת מום
כסתומה דמי. Aval ba'alat mum kistumah dami. One minute. So you want
to tell me though that if you had just three cows there
and they had blemishes that would have the same status of money?
That's what the argument is. So מאי אריא מעות? Mai arya maot?
So why is it only giving the example if you've got money
you can use it to go ahead and you know go towards
an עולה? Olah? So לימא היתה לו בהמה בעלת מום יפלו לנדבה.
Leima haitah lo behemah ba'alat mum yiplu linedavah. Meaning this is already
a better question. Why are you contrasting unspecified money to specified animals?
Right, you're leaving off a lot of middle cases. Right, why don't
you just, yeah, so the גמרא Gemara often goes to extremes, but
okay be a little bit clearer. Say if you've got unspecified animals
with blemishes then then the money goes towards a נדבה. Nedavah. But
if you've got specified animals or even non-specified animals but they don't
have blemishes then the money doesn't go to a נדבה, Nedavah, then
you're stuck. Right, why not contrast closer cases? You know, okay, if
there really are these differences. So it sounds like why only money?
Anything that's not money would be no good. If it really are
certain types of animals are like money, animals unspecified with blemishes, why
not say that? So the גמרא Gemara says הכי נמי. Hachi nami.
You know what? Fine, that's included in the idea of money. So
בעלת מום למאי קדישא? Ba'alat mum lemai kedishah? If it's got a
blemish, what's the sanctity going for? לדמי, Lidmei, ultimately it's going to
be sold. So דמי היינו מעות. Demei hayinu maot. So that's what
we meant when we said money. Okay, it's like obvious. Money means
anything that can be sold. Which is I think how we would
have read it, right? We said you've got a pile of unspecified
money, you do one thing. On the other hand, if you've sanctified
your חטאת, chatas, you've sanctified your עולה, olah, you've sanctified your שלמים,
shelamim, I would have said any case that you have not clearly
identified which is your חטאת, chatas, which is your עולה, olah, which
is your שלמים, shelamim, it goes into the money category, right? So
if I had a guess which is the bigger category, I'd assume
the money category is everything.
Exactly specifying חטאת, chatas, עולה, olah, and שלמים, shelamim, that's the case
where there's a different הלכה halacha and that's basically what the גמרא's
Gemara saying, okay? So basically what we've done is we're working out
this special הלכה halacha that unspecified money goes towards an עולה, olah,
does it apply only to cash or things that are seen like
cash, which the גמרא's Gemara willing to consider maybe animals with a
מום mum or whatever, or does it basically apply to like pretty
much everything, okay? And even within the idea that it's only things
like cash, there's a question of like exactly where do you put
the בהמה behema with a מום? mum? Is the בהמה behema with
a מום mum in the cash category or in the non-cash category?
But again, this is an assumption that this is a formal הלכה
halacha of a pile of money or this is one approach in
the גמרא Gemara that we started with, right? There's pushback and it
says it should be not so limited, but the limiting approach is
it only basically applies to money and to other things that we're
willing to consider to be like cash, among them is animals with
a מום mum that the קדושה kedusha doesn't become an obstacle and
they're seen as something that's able to be sold pretty regularly. All
right, so I didn't get to your questions but we're going to
end here because it's...